Guide to the Examinations Collection, 1868 - 1970
Examinations Collection, 1868 - 1970
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-149
2.5
2
7
1
Wesleyan University exams reflect the changing curriculum between 1868 and 1970. The nineteenth century Wesleyan curriculum allowed students to major in general areas of knowledge, while the twentieth century curriculum saw the rise of numerous departments. The use of entrance examinations, a standard in the 1800s, were eliminated.
This collection comprises some 800 examinations given at Wesleyan from 1868 to 1970. Of these, close to 300 are from the 19th century. The 1960s are relatively poorly represented, with only 38 items. About 480 examinations are printed, 44 are manuscript and the remainder are either typed or mimeographed. Examinations dated after 1930 are almost exclusively comprehensive examinations, while earlier examinations include entrance examinations, mid-term and final examinations, and competitive examinations for named prizes awarded for academic excellence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired prior to 1980.
Historical Note
In 1868, when this collection of examinations begins, there were only 148 students enrolled at Wesleyan University. By 1970, the end date of this collection, the student enrollment was up to 1,393 students and the school had been admitting women for two years. In the latter part of the 19th century, the curriculum was a very different format than what it became by the late 1960s. In the 1860s, the courses for the students were pre-planned each term according to their academic focus. There were requirements for admission to the university in Latin, Greek, Mathematics, and English, although if students wished to only take literary and scientific courses, they did not have to be familiar with Latin and Greek. There was a general course of study that included languages, mathematics, various sciences, government, philosophy, and history. There was also a scientific course of study offered with more focus on the sciences and fewer courses in Latin and Greek. Later in the 19th century, a student could chose among the classical course in which he or she earned a bachelor of arts, the Latin-scientific course in which he or she earned a bachelor of philosophy, and the scientific course in which he or she earned a bachelor of science.
Beginning in the early 20th century, new departments were established and students were able to choose courses among the different departments. The departments included Latin, Greek, Hebrew, German, romance languages, English literature, English language, public speaking, history, economics and social science, philosophy, psychology, ethics and religion, mathematics, physics, astronomy, chemistry, geology, biology, physical education, military science and tactics, and the required freshman course, fundamentals of student life. The departments were divided into three categories or divisions which still exist today: arts and humanities, social sciences, and natural sciences and math. Students were and are still required to take courses in all three divisions of the curriculum in order to ensure a well rounded liberal education. By the mid-20th century, several departments were added to include art, classics (a combination of the Latin and Greek departments), music, philosophy and ethics, and religion. More departments were added to the curriculum following World War II, including Chinese, theater, and Russian. In the 1961-1962 catalog, the section on the background and history of the university states that the years since the end of World War II have been characterized by self-study and controlled experimentation seeking ways in which to make liberal education more meaningful and vital to each student. By this point, the College of Letters and the College of Social Sciences (also known as the Public Affairs Program) had been established. With the exception of a few additional departments, the curriculum has remained similar to what it became in the early 1960s.
Collection Overview
This collection comprises some 800 examinations given at Wesleyan from 1868 to 1970. Of these, close to 300 are from the nineteenth century. The 1960s are relatively poorly represented, with only 38 items. About 480 examinations are printed, 44 are manuscript and the remainder are either typed or mimeographed. Examinations dated after 1930 are almost exclusively comprehensive examinations, while earlier examinations include entrance examinations, mid-term and final examinations, and competitive examinations for named prizes awarded for academic excellence.
The present collection is drawn from several sources. A large number of the nineteenth century examinations are contained in a scrapbook presented by the Eclectic fraternity. Most comprehensive examinations from the late 1920s through the late 1950s were catalogued by department for the Wesleyan University Archives. With the exception of those contained in seven bound volumes, these comprehensive examinations have been boxed together by department. The following list integrates holdings found in two archival boxes, seven bound volumes, and the Eclectic scrapbook.
Collection Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically by department. It is noted whether materials are found in the boxes, the volumes, or the scrapbook.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Curricula.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Examinations --History.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Art
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1951, 1956, 1959, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Astronomy
    - 1887, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1885, 1887
  - Biology
    - 1887
    - Physiology, 1890
  - Chemistry
    - 1887
  - Classics: general
    - 1936, 1941, 1950, 1952, 1953, 1956, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Classics: Greek
    - Entrance examinations, circa 1885, 1893-1895, 1903, and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1893 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1883, 1884, 1889 and undated
  - Classics: Latin
    - Entrance examinations, 1882, 1894, 1895, 1898, 1902-1904, 1918, 1925, 1934-1937 and undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      34 total exams.
    - Mid-year and final examinations, 1889-1921, 1931, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      90 total exams.
      Latin I: 24
      Latin II: 21
      Latin III: 15
      Latin IV: 11
      Latin V: 7
      Advanced levels (VI-XII): 14
    - Examinations on topics in Roman history and literature, 1868-1894 and undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      47 total exams, of which 15 are dated. Some are called Sophomore Examination or Junior Examination.
    - Examinations on topics in Roman history and literature, 1875, 1883, 1890 and undated
      77 total exams, of which 3 are dated.
    - Examinations for prizes
      - Ayres Prize, 1893-1895, 1898-1900, 1905, 1907, 1909, 1911 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
        16 total exams, of which 12 are dated.
      - Ayres Prize, 1877 and undated
      - Phi Beta Kappa, 1884, 1894, 1895, 1898, 1899, 1907 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
        9 total exams, of which 6 are dated.
      - Phi Beta Kappa, 1877, 1883
      - Sherman Prize, 1883, 1889, 1919 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Spinney Prize, undated
        2 total exams.
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1928, 1932, 1933, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Economics
    - Mid-year and final examinations (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Economics 1: 1893, 1932, 1935
      - Economics 5: 1932, 1935, 1936
      - Economics 7: 1932, 1935, 1936
    - Comprehensive examinations
      - 1964, 1965, 1966, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 1926-1944, 1946-1952, 1954-1958 (Volume 1)
  - English
    - Elocution, 1889
    - Grammar, undated
    - Literature
      - Mid-year and final examinations, 1873, 1881, 1884, 1899, 1900, 1901, 1903, 1905, 1906, 1907, 1910, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Includes A List of Books Recommended for Freshman Reading, and Courses of Collateral Reading for the Junior Class in English Literature (2 versions)
      - 1884, 1885, 1889, 1890
    - Comprehensive examinations
      - 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 1926, 1942, 1944, 1958 (Volume 2)
    - Rhetoric
      - 1891, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1888, 1890
  - Geology
    - Mid-year or final examination, 1889
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1936, 1939-1940, 1942, 1944, 1948, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - German
    - Entrance examinations, 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      All years except 1901, 1903, and 1911.
    - Mid-year and final examinations
      - German I, 1891, 1904-1919, 1925, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        26 exams total.
      - German I, 1887
      - German II, 1884, 1901-1904, 1906-1910, 1913-1920, 1923, 1924, 1932 and undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
        17 exams total.
      - German II, 1886 and undated
      - German III, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - German V, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Comprehensive examinations
      - 1962, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - 1931-1941 (Volume 3)
  - Government
    - Comprehensive examinations
      - 1962, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - 1933-1958 (Volume 4)
    - Mid-year and final examinations in Constitutional Law
      - 1894 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - 1884
    - Political Economy examination, 1887 and undated
  - History
    - Entrance examinations, 1895, 1899, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mid-year and final examinations
      - 1900, 1910, 1913, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - 1883, 1887, 1890
    - Comprehensive examinations
      - 1963, 1966, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - 1933-1936, 1941-1943, 1946-1952, 1954-1958 (Volume 5)
  - Mathematics
    - Entrance examinations, 1885, 1882, 1887, 1902, 1908 and undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mid-year and final examinations
      - Algebra, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Algebra, 1881
      - Calculus, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - College mathematics, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - College mathematics, 1879
      - Geometry, 1868, 1888, 1889, 1891, 1903, 1904, 1905, 1906, 1907, 1908, 1909, 1910, 1911, 1912, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Geometry, 1875, 1882, 1883, 1885-1887, 1889
      - Trigonometry, 1891, 1906, 1910, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Examinations for prizes
      - Ayres prize, 1912, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Rice prize, 1909, 1910, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Surveying, 1886
  - Music
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1950-1953, 1955, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy
    - Mid-year and final examinations, 1887, 1890
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1959, 1962-1967, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1931-1936, 1938-1943, 1945, 1947-1955, 1958, 1959 (Volume 6)
    - Ethics, 1886
    - Logic, 1883, 1889
  - Physics
    - General exams, 1878, 1885, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mechanics
      - 1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1888, 1890
  - Psychology
    - Mid-year and final examinations
      - 1899 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1877, 1890
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1934-1938, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Religion
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Christian Evidence, 1887, 1890
  - Romance Languages
    - French mid-year and final examinations
      - 1884, 1893, 1899, 1902, 1907, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1882, 1884, 1887, 1890
    - French comprehensive examinations
      - 1945-1950, 1952, 1953, 1956, 1957, 1961, 1962, 1964, 1965, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1926-1943 (Volume 7)
    - Spanish comprehensive examinations, 1950, 1959, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Social Sciences and College of Social Studies
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1940-1942, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Theater
    - Comprehensive examinations, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)